A Guide to the Speeches Delivered at the University of Virginia, 1904-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Speeches Delivered at the University of Virginia 1904-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
30/9/5.071
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content
In [1938?] Lester J. Cappon sent out a circular letter seeking copies of every address given at the University or by University professors for files in the Virginia Room. Many of the speeches in this collection appear to have been given in response to Cappon's plea.
The collection contains lectures in a theology series, 1936 -1940, by Mortimer Adler, Norman P. Cohen, James M. Egan, O.P., Frank A. Geldard, Lewis M. Hammond, D. Clark Hyde, L. F. Kinney, William H. Laird, S. Vernon McCasland, Marcus B. Mallett, A. T. Mollegen, Howard Newman (notes only), J. Winfree Smith, William Kyle Smith, Carroll Mason Sparrow, Joseph Strause (notes only), and William S. Weedon. Sparrow's essay on "The measure of measurement" was later published in Voyages and Cargoes.
The collection also contains lectures in a great authors series by A.D. Fraser, W.A. Montgomery and Frederic T. Wood.
Speeches on University of Virginia topics include the honor system by Virginius Dabney; Paul B. Barringer by Roy Flannegan; a debate before the Jefferson Society by Robert W. Hoel; the 8th Evacuation Hospital by H.E. Jordan; a comparison of the University in 1896 and 1924 by James M. Page; the "gay nineties" at Virginia by Lewis C. Williams.
Other speakers include Sir Harold Bellman, A. D. Fraser, Garrard Glenn, James Hart, W. Edwin Hemphill, A. A. Hill, C[linton?] N[ewton?] Howard, William H. Laird, Ivey F. Lewis, John C. Metcalf, Julius M. Parmlee, Charles Pergler, Homer Richey, Joseph K. Roberts,Karl R. Wallace, Sumner Welles, Jennings C. Wise, Frederick T. Wood, David M. Wright.
Miscellaneous items include a catalog of prints by Oscar Gieberich on exhibit, 1939.
Contents List
- Correspondence concerning a plan to assemble various speeches given at the University of Virginia, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Divine and Human Law by Mortimer Adler, 1938 May 1 (Box-folder 1:2)
- The Student Dilemma by Sir Harold Bellman, 1938 May 9 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Judaism by Normann P. Cohen, 1939 February 26 (Box-folder 1:4)
- The Honor System's First 100 Years by Virginius Dabney, n.d. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Acquisitive Society by James M. Egan, 1940 November 17 (Box-folder 1:6)
- The Person of the Father, Son and Holy Ghost by James M. Egan, 1939 January 8 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Paul B. Barringer by Dr. Roy Flannegan, 1941 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Homer by A.D. Fraser, 1939 February 15 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Science- Demonstrative Knowledge by Frank Arthur Gerald, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Catalogue of Prints by Oscar Gieberich, 1939 May 14 (Box-folder 1:11)
- What is a Liberal? by Garrard Glenn, 1938 March 7 (Box-folder 1:12)
- The Apostle's Creed- The great Christian principles by Lewis M. Hammond, 1940 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Freedom by Lewis M. Hammond, 1937 January 17 (Box-folder 1:14)
- The Mode of Union by Lewis M. Hammond, 1939 February 5 (Box-folder 1:15)
- The Psychological Man- Sigmund Freud by Lewis M. Hammond, 1937 January 31 (Box-folder 1:16)
- The Sacraments by Lewis M. Hammond, 1937 May 2 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Citizens in the Making by James Hart, 1938 February 17 (Box-folder 1:18)
- Democracy by James Hart, 1939 February 17 (Box-folder 1:19)
- Business Archives in Virginia by W. Hemphill, 1939 April 21 (Box-folder 1:20)
- Development of Languages by A.A. Hill, 1933 (Box-folder 1:21)
- Debate Affirmative by Robert W. Hoel, 1939 May 5 (Box-folder 1:22)
- England in a Troubled World by Clinton Howard, 1939 July 25 (Box-folder 1:23)
- The Democratic State: Economics and Politics by D.C. Hyde, 1939 October 19 (Box-folder 1:24)
- Evacuation Hospital no. 8 by Harvey J. Jordan, 1942 May 13 (Box-folder 1:25)
- Christ's Prayer and Priesthood by Lawrence F. Kinney, 1939 February 26 (Box-folder 1:26)
- The Perfections and Imperfections of Christ by William H. Laird, 1939 February 12 (Box-folder 1:27)
- The Dilemma of the Church by William H. Laird, 1940 January 14 (Box-folder 1:28)
- The New Testament Law of Love: Revelation and Christian Action by William H. Laird, 1940 October 27 (Box-folder 1:29)
- Repression of the Scientific Spirit by Ivey F. Lewis, 1939 February 17 (Box-folder 1:30)
- The Christian View of Sin, Grace, and Salvation by S.V. McCasland, 1947 (Box-folder 1:31)
- Democracy- Sophistic or Socratic? by Marcus B. Mallet, 1939 October 22 (Box-folder 1:32)
- Prolegomenon to any Doctrine of Sacramentalism by Marcus B. Mallet, 1942 February 22 (Box-folder 1:33)
- Loxology by Maxwell C. Maxwell (Print Announcement), 1939 February 3 (Box-folder 1:34)
- The Elizabethan Lyric by John C. Metcalf, n.d. (Box-folder 1:35)
- The Individual in Education by John C. Metcalf, n.d. (Box-folder 1:36)
- Untitled Speech by John C. Metcalf, n.d. (Box-folder 1:37)
- Man as Self-Maker and Self-Governor by Albert T. Mollegan, 1942 January 25 (Box-folder 1:38)
- Virgil's Place in the Modern World by W.A. Montgomery, 1939 October 13 (Box-folder 1:39)
- Protestantism by Howard Newman, 1939 February 26 (Box-folder 1:40)
- Character by James M. Page, 1930 February 16 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Mathematics by James M. Page, 1904 May 18 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Merano by James M. Page, 1932 March 31 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Phi Beta Kappa by James M. Page, 1905 December 5 (Box-folder 2:4)
- The University of Virginia in 1896 and in 1924 by James M. Page, 1924 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Development of a National Transportation Policy by Julius H. Pharmlee, 1939 February 6 (Box-folder 2:6)
- The Triassic Rocks of Virginia by Joseph K. Roberts, 1938 December 28 (Box-folder 2:7)
- The Fitness of the Incarnation by J. Winfree Smith, 1939 January 29 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Atonement- Redemption by William K. Smith, 1937 October 31 (Box-folder 2:9)
- The Old Testament Hebraic Concept of Peace by William K. Smith, 1947 January (Box-folder 2:10)
- Intuition by Carroll M. Sparrow, 1938 January 9 (Box-folder 2:11)
- Knowledge and Virtue by Carroll M. Sparrow, 1939 November 26 (Box-folder 2:12)
- The Measurement of Measurement by Carroll M. Sparrow, n.d. (Box-folder 2:13)
- Persons and Relations in the Trinity by Carroll M. Sparrow, 1938 November 20 (Box-folder 2:14)
- The Scientific Man by Carroll M. Sparrow, 1937 February 14 (Box-folder 2:15)
- Essay on Evolution, untitled, by Carroll M. Sparrow, n.d., Accompanied by a note dated January 6, 1943. (Box-folder 2:16)
- Essay on organic development, untitled, by Carroll M. Sparrow, n.d. (Box-folder 2:17)
- Essay on philosophy, untitled and incomplete, by Carroll M. Sparrow, n.d. (Box-folder 2:18)
- Essay on philosophy of science, untitled, by Carroll M. Sparrow, n.d. (Box-folder 2:19)
- Manuscript of an untitled book, Chapter 1 Babel by Carroll M. Sparrow, n.d. (Box-folder 2:20)
- Catholicism by Joseph Strause, 1939 February 26 (Box-folder 2:21)
- Instruction in Speech in the Public Schools by Karl R. Wallace, 1939 August 2 (Box-folder 2:22)
- Creation by William S. Weedon, 1941 November 9 (Box-folder 2:23)
- The Love of Institutions by William S. Weedon, 1936 February 23 (Box-folder 2:24)
- Natural Man by William S. Weedon, 1937 February 21 (Box-folder 2:25)
- Philosophic Wisdom by William S. Weedon, 1938 January 23 (Box-folder 2:26)
- Natural Rights of Mankind by Sumner Welles, 1939 April 13 (Box-folder 2:27)
- The 'Gay Nineties' at Virginia by Lewis C. Williams, n.d. (Box-folder 2:28)
- The Surest Means of American Defense by Jennings C. Wise, 1924, 1939 Reprint. (Box-folder 2:29)
- What Should Be Our Attitude Toward the War? Jennings C. Wise, 1939 November 27 (Box-folder 2:30)
- Heinrich Heine by Frederic T. Wood, 1940 November 11 (Box-folder 2:31)
- Music of the German Romanticist by Frederic T. Wood, 1939 February 11 (Box-folder 2:32)
- Essence of the Keynesian by David M. Wright, 2:33 (Box-folder 2:33)